Today's דף daf is י"א, yud aleph,
we pick up with a new משנה. mishnah. The previous משנה mishnah
had discussed the basic difference about the כתובה ksuva for a woman
who is a בתולה besulah and a non-בתולה, besulah, the difference between
200 and 100 based on the biblical verses, and the תורה torah
only knows about a מוהר, mohar, which isn't a כתובה, ksuva, it's
an upfront payment, but anyway, but it's the basis for כתובה. ksuva.
It only knows of a מוהר mohar for a בתולה. besulah. חכמים
chachamim instituted all say they switched that upfront payment to a payment
at the end, they turned מוהר mohar into כתובה ksuva and then
they also instituted a כתובה ksuva for an אלמנה. almanah. And we
now go on, the remaining of the משניות mishnayot here talk about
various issues which are more questionable and borderline whether they are 200
or 100, whether it's in the category of בתולה besulah or אלמנה.
almanah. One case we already dealt with in the משנה mishnah is
a woman who is a בתולה besulah but has been married but
was only קידושין kiddushin and not נישואין nissuim and therefore her status
remains that of a בתולה. besulah. So now we turn to the
next משנה. mishnah.
There's already
a question here. Is it legally accurate to describe the כתובה ketubah
money as what we call alimony?
No, it's not fully accurate. I mean, it's close to that because
in a case of a divorce, right, in a case of a
divorce, that's what she gets. That's all she gets, it's a one-sum
lump payment, but she also gets it in the case that the
husband dies, so it's also a substitute for inheritance because the wife
does not inherit in the
תורה. torah. So it serves both purposes, right? Right, exactly. מוהר's mohar
in this week's פרשה. parsha. So now let's take a look here
at the משנה. mishnah. הגיורת hagioret top of דף י"א עמוד א'.
daf yud aleph amud aleph. הגיורת והשבויה והשפחה. hagioret vehashvuya vehashifcha. So
you have a convert, a woman who converted, a woman who is
taken captive, taken captive, it's assumed that she was raped, or a
woman who is a maidservant who was a maidservant who was a
slave, a non-Jewish slave. Okay, also therefore assumed that the first and
the last case as non-Jews, the assumption was that they, you know,
that they are sexually promiscuous. So therefore שנתפדו ושנתגיירו ושנשתחררו, shenifdu veshenitgayeru
veshenishtachreru,
if they were redeemed, converted, or freed, right,
when a slave is freed he or she becomes free. As Michael
points out, the verbs don't match the nouns. We might have something
to do with how, you know, you say the short words first,
נתפדו nifdu before נתגיירו. nitgayeru. Doesn't explain why you say שבויה shvuya
before גיורת. gioret. Anyway, פחותה
מבת שלוש שנים ויום אחד, pachusa mibnas shalosh shanim veyom echad, if
these transitions happened and they became Jewish and not enslaved and not
held captive and they were still under three years old, then כתובתן
מאתיים. ksuvasan masayim. Then you assume that they are still virgins. Actually,
what you wind up assuming is that even if somebody had done
an act even if had raped them, had had an act of
sex with them, it would not have
the hymen would have grown back. That's the assumption the גמרא gemara
makes. There's actually two assumptions because what we're going to get to
in the next משנה mishnah is what defines being a virgin. Does
it mean never having had sex or does it mean having the
hymen intact? So an act of sex with a girl under three
halachically is not defined as an act of sex either. So therefore
if these, if these, you know, essentially baby girls had been somebody
had done an act of sex with them which essentially has raped
them, it a would not be considered an act of sex and
b it would not have be considered to have prevented their, you
know, ruptured the hymen or the hymen would grow back, okay. So
we'll see in the next משנה, mishnah, you know, the possibility of
one of those without the other, but the assumption is under three
you have neither of those conditions. ויש להן טענת בתולים veyesh lahen
ta'anas besulim and therefore since they're assumed to be virgins, if on
the wedding night it's discovered they're not virgins, the husband has a
legitimate claim: I was expecting my wife to be a virgin, she's
not, and then it has all the various consequences in terms of
the כתובה ksuva and so on. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. gemara. This גמרא gemara now does not really focus us on
the כתובה ksuva aspect of that משנה mishnah but talking about כתובה
ksuva being a שעת קטנות, shas katnus, we've had so many different
topics come up until now, and today we have the topic of
גר קטן, ger katan, converting
someone who is still a minor. And the basic סוגיא sugya of
גר קטן ger katan is this next, is this following, is this
עמוד amud right in front of us. So let's take a look.
אמר רב הונא, amar rav huna, said רב הונא, rav huna, גר
קטן, ger katan, somebody who is converted as a minor, מטבילין אותו
על דעת בית דין. matbilin oso al da'as beis din. So you
convert him on the sort of, you know, on the supervision of
בית דין beis din with the knowledge and approval of בית דין.
beis din. Now what does that mean? Somebody comes, so what's the
case? Could be a baby, could be a case a baby is
left on the doorstep or you adopt a baby, adopt a baby
which is a very common circumstance, and therefore you want to convert
him. But the case in the גמרא, gemara, the case that's assumed
here could just be, I mean, it's funny, the easiest case to
imagine and רש"י rashi describes the reverse is that the father is
Jewish and the mother is not Jewish and the father wants to
convert his biological child. Okay, that would be another case, right? That
also happens a lot. it's a mixed marriage and you want to
convert the children. That's another case of גר קטן. Ger Katan. I
mean, the case about the child that's left on the doorstep is
a very sensitive one as you could imagine, you know, because also
between like the Jews and their Christian neighbors
and what have you, anyway so there's like you know because and
you know because the Christians also deal with a story about what
happens if you steal a Jewish baby and baptize it does it
remain Christian you know so it's a kind of is it done
against the parents' will so let's try to deal with an easier
case like you know adopted or a child of a mixed marriage
and therefore the father's Jewish mother is not but רש"י Rashi describes
the case as the reverse the mother the father is not around
and the mother comes to convert the child now if the mother
was Jewish you wouldn't need to convert him so presumably it's the
mother herself converted let's say and now she's also coming to convert
the child now it's interesting to look at one line in רש"י
Rashi רש"י Rashi says first line of רש"י Rashi גר קטן אם
אין לו אב ואמו הביאתו להתגייר Ger Katan im ein lo av
ve-imo hevi-ato lehitgayer
so again you have to explain that the mother was not Jewish
and now she's Jewish but it's interesting that רש"י Rashi underlines the
fact of אין לו אב ein lo av and presumably it's very
important להלכה lehalacha because most of the case you know I don't
know the exact numbers but I think it's safe to say at
least probably about at least 50% of cases of גר קטן Ger
Katan are cases where the father's Jewish and the mother is not
so why would it be any different according to רש"י Rashi if
the father was around which is you know is רש"י Rashi just
describing a common scenario actually that's a less common scenario so many
פוסקים poskim assume and actually it sounds this way that the way
it sounds like שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch פוסק paskens this way that
if the father the biological father is there and let's say he's
Jewish you don't need the דעת בית דין da'as beis din okay
because the question here becomes a very central question who needs this
idea of דעת בית דין da'as beis din and the גמרא Gemara
in a minute is going to say that it's based on the
idea of זכין לאדם שלא בפניו zachin leadam shelo befanav you can
do something for somebody's benefit even though they're not around why do
you need so let's actually read that and then we'll come back
and discuss בית דין beis din and the father so the גמרא
Gemara says מאי קא משמע לן mai ka mashma lan what is
this telling me so דזכות הוא לו dezchus hu lo that it's
a benefit for somebody to be Jewish וזכין לאדם שלא בפניו ve-zachin
leadam shelo befanav and that you can do a merit for somebody
not in their presence because the child is not considered to be
present because you do not have you know he does he's not
doesn't you don't have his full consent he's not there as an
adult right so okay so one minute okay so ואין חבין לאדם
ve'ein chavin leadam same story בית דין beis din would do it
ואין חבין לאדם שלא בפניו ve'ein chavin leadam shelo befanav so you
so so are you telling me that the point is that even
though the child is not considered to be present to give his
own consent and approval to it because he's not an adult and
able to do that that we can do it on his behalf
because you can do something that is meritorious for somebody not in
their presence and this is considered not in their presence that's a
חידוש chidush Michael let me give you a hint and is that
considered and this is considered not in the presence so so it's
obvious we know all these principles so someone says no we might
know the principle of זכין לאדם שלא בפניו zachin leadam shelo befanav
but I think as Michael was trying to say it's not obvious
that we identify this as a זכות zchus מהו דתימא mahu d'teima
I might have thought עובד כוכבים בהפקירא ניחא ליה oveid kochavim be-hefkira
nicha lei that a non-Jew would prefer the freedom הפקר hefker the
freedom the non-restrained life of being a non-Jew and therefore we cannot
come here and objectively say it is better for this infant to
be Jewish you know it's an interesting question how do you define
זכות zchus objective or subjective right when we might it would be
hard for the גמרא Gemara to say that we could say that
we would not say objectively it's better to be Jewish right pretty
funny to feel try to feel like a sense of you know
pride about being a judge if you don't think that objectively it's
better to be a Jew so obviously we're going to say objectively
it's better but not necessarily true subjectively non-Jews might not want it
they might feel that they'd rather have a life of an of
of of lack of restraint so unfettered דהא קיימא לן de-ha kaima
lan because in general we hold דעבד וודאי בהפקירא ניחא ליה de-eved
vadai be-hefkira nicha lei
that for a slave we certainly assume that he would rather remain
a slave and have a life of freedom than become freed and
become a Jew which is deep you know deeply troubling this week's
פרשה parsha about freeing the slave right of course it's a Hebrew
slave but you know certainly you know with you know the whole
idea about saying oh yeah well the slaves would rather remain slaves
than they would become free that's an idea that actually gets discussed
about can somebody for example you know
can I if I have a slave free the slave not in
the slave's presence because and in appoint Michael to be the agent
for the slave to receive his writ of manumission his גט שחרור
get shichrur because oh it's all for his benefit so anybody around
this table would say of course it's true of course it's for
his benefit to be free of course you can do it not
in his presence but the גמרא Gemara says no not necessarily he
might prefer a life of being a slave because it's an unrestrained
life okay so
well that's true okay so again maybe that's true again maybe what
we're saying is that subjectively that there might be true even if
objectively we'll say it's obviously the wrong thing obviously it's better to
be free but subjectively sometimes people maybe like that
state so anyway so the גמרא Gemara so we say that we
say that we can't assume it's a merit for a slave to
be free דעבד וודאי בהפקירא ניחא ליה de-eved vadai be-hefkira nicha lei
so again maybe that's true So therefore I would say that maybe
the state would be about a non-Jew. The גמרא Gemara assumes that
slaves have even less restraint than non-Jews, not just in terms of
legal restraint, like הלכה, Halacha, like שבע מצוות בני נח, Sheva Mitzvot
Bnei Noach, but in terms of what the nature of their life
is, you know, because slaves don't have married life, it was the
rabbis assumed that it meant that therefore they were more freely promiscuous
than simple standard non-Jews, you know, who lived in a more, you
know, in a who their societal norms they they had married life,
so therefore less promiscuous. So there's like a lot of assumptions here
being made through the eyes of people that weren't, you know, that
aren't slaves. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara says so when it comes
to slaves we certainly say they prefer to be free, so presumably
we would say the same about non-Jews, and maybe we couldn't say
that it's to their benefit. So and again, even though objectively it
would be but not subjectively. קמשמע לן, Kamashma lan, so therefore it's
telling me that we do consider it to be his benefit. הני
מילי גדול, Hani milei gadol, that's true by an adult, we could
say that subjectively it might not be to his benefit, דטעים טעים
דאיסורא, de-taim taim de-issura, that he had the taste of the forbidden
fruit. Okay, he knows what a life of like greater, you know,
like sexual freedom and other types of freedoms is like, and then
we say he's not ready to give that up. אבל קטן, Aval
katan, but for a minor, זכות הוא לו, zechus hu lo, he's
never had the taste of the forbidden fruit, so subjectively where he
is right now, right, although it's funny, like you don't ask him
because what his actual דעת daas is irrelevant because he's it's not
like considered like meaningful yet for legal terms because he's a minor,
but if you're trying to assess would he would it subjectively be
in his best interest, you put yourself in his place but you
assess it based on based on his current, you know, psychological reality
and his current life experiences, and based on that you would say
he would also subjectively be in his best interest. So what we
have established is we have a principle you can do something for
somebody for their best interest. We're going to assert that we're objectively
and even subjectively going to consider this to be for best interest,
and therefore we can go ahead and do it even though there's
no adult, right, like, you know, who's the adult in the room?
So the בית דין Beis Din is the only adult in the
room, and nevertheless even though there's no adult representing his side, we
can approve of it on his behalf. Now the question becomes, why
do you need this whole idea of זכין? zachin? Why do you
need the בית דין Beis Din to do anything? What role exactly
are they doing? And the simple answer is basically what the language
I've been using, which is somebody has to, you know, go ahead
and approve of it. Like, it's not a question of necessarily like
would it work if you didn't do that, like maybe you could
ask that question too. But the first question is, who allows you
to do it? Who in what way is it at all considered
conscionable, unconscionable to go ahead and to change a person's status, you
know, without their acquiescence, right? And you could then say and even
בדיעבד, be-di-eved, something that basically is about changing my personal status, if
it's if it's against my will or if I didn't give my
say so, if I didn't give my okay to it, why should
that why should you why should that be effective, a changing of
my status? So basically what בית דין's Beis Din role here is,
is to sort of give the approval, you know, they are able
to say it's like parents, right, we make decisions for our children
all the time, we decide what school we're going to send them
to, we make a million decisions for our children, right? Why is
that, you know, we're legally entitled to do so, we try to
do it on their best behalf, you know, hopefully good parents do,
okay, and we're legally entitled to do so, okay? So here it
says who is legally entitled? Normally you can't force somebody to convert
against their will. Who's giving their will here? And what we're saying
is the בית דין Beis Din are in the position to represent
the interests of the minor because and because they deem it to
be his benefit, and therefore they're the ones that are giving the
will to say that we are okay, you know, that to convert.
That's presumably the structure the way it works. And therefore now we
understand רש"י, Rashi, because רש"י Rashi says that if there's a biological
Jewish father, right, then you don't need בית דין, Beis Din, because
the father makes the decision for the kid. Parents are always making
decisions for the kids. So the father can say, right, now why
did רש"י Rashi דוקא dafka father not mother? Again, an assumption that
we're dealing with a patriarchy, so the father's the head of the
family. Okay, so anyway, so therefore that is the role that בית
דין Beis Din is doing, that is the role that a biological
father would do, and that's sort of the idea sort of basically
giving the acquiescence, giving the will to in order to, it's yes,
you, you know, in order to go ahead and do the and
to present the will and the agreement of the other side. Now,
I need to say something which is that that is totally a
hundred percent פשט pshat of the גמרא. Gemara.
Some אחרונים, achronim, and there actually is like maybe a תוספות Tosfos
or whatever here and there possibility of a ראשון, Rishon, but it
develops most more in the אחרונים, achronim, try to say בית דין
Beis Din is doing something totally different. What they say that בית
דין's Beis Din role here is, is not to give their will
and acquiescence, but to be stand in for the act of קבלת
מצוות. kabbalas mitzvos. Okay, this גמרא Gemara doesn't discuss קבלת מצוות kabbalas
mitzvos at all, and most ראשונים Rishonim say what happened to the
קבלת מצוות kabbalas mitzvos here, right? Who's accepting the minor isn't accepting
upon him or herself to live a life according to תורה Torah
and מצוות? mitzvos? So there's basically two answers. In the ראשונים *rishonim*.
One is, okay, in a case of a minor you don't need
it and maybe in a case of adult you do, but in
the case of a minor you don't. Or the other answer might
be that well when the minor becomes an adult and we'll see
that later and agrees to continue living a Jewish life, that sort
of constitutes a קבלת מצוות *kabbalas mitzvos* or something, like a quasi-,
you know, a pseudo-קבלת מצוות *kabbalas mitzvos*. But some אחרונים *achronim* say
no, you know who's doing the קבלת מצוות *kabbalas mitzvos*? The בית
דין Beis Din *beis din*. That the reason the גמרא Gemara *gemara*
says that בית דין Beis Din? *beis din* plays a role of
זכין לאדם שלא בפניו Zachin leadam shelo befanyov. *zachin l'adam shelo befanav*
is in order that they represent the side of the minor and
they are being מקבל מצוות *mekabel mitzvos* for the minor, in, you
know, sort of representing the minor. That is not at all פשט
*pshat* in the גמרא Gemara *gemara*. This גמרא Gemara *gemara* doesn't even
mention a hint of קבלת מצוות *kabbalas mitzvos*, but certain- but that
is how a number of אחרונים *achronim* read it. This all leads
to three very distinct camps when it comes to the question of
converting minors, and as I said, a classic example is a case
of an intermarriage and you want to convert the kids. So there
are those that say you don't- let's- the simple sense is you
don't need קבלת מצוות *kabbalas mitzvos* at all. We're not even going
to discuss קבלת מצוות *kabbalas mitzvos*. Now now now, the only- right,
right, maybe in the future, but let's assume even not. The only
thing we're going to discuss is, is it a זכות *zechus* for
the minor? So then the issue comes up, well let's say the
parents are not observant. Can you say it's a merit for somebody
to be Jewish if they're raised in a non-, in any non-observant
home? Because then they're not- they're going to have all the obligations
of מצוות *mitzvos* but they're not going to be, you know, trained
and prepared and to live a life of מצוות *mitzvos*. Is that
really for their benefit? And then you have a debate. Some say
yes, objectively, first of all, whatever happened to all the מצוות בין
אדם לחברו *mitzvos bein adam l'chaveiro* the person is going to get?
Not just מצוות בין אדם למקום *mitzvos bein adam l'makom*. Secondly, maybe
you could say objectively כל ישראל יש להם חלק לעולם הבא *kol
Yisrael yesh lahem chelek l'olam haba*, maybe objectively it's better to be
a Jew, even a non-observant Jew, than to be a non-Jew. Fascinating
sort of theological religious type of question. So there's definitely a camp
that says even if they're not going to do a life of
מצוות *mitzvos* or that's most likely, they're not being raised in an
observant home, it's still a זכות *zechus*. By the way, all of
this is better if you have a Jewish father based on that
רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, then you don't have to argue זכות *zechus*. You
have a Jewish father, he gives it his okay. But if you
don't have a biological Jewish father, you have to argue זכות *zechus*.
So therefore you have one camp that says even in a non-observant
home. You have another camp that says no, you don't need- you
need to be able to say that it's to make it reasonably
a זכות *zechus*, to make it a זכות *zechus*, you have to
be able to say that you're putting him on, you're giving him
a good chance to live an observant life. You don't have to
know one hundred percent, but you're giving him a reasonable fighting odds.
So therefore, that's when, you know, they talk about are you going
to send him to Jewish day school, are you going to a
שול shul *shul*? We might not demand that the parents be observant
or fully observant, you know, maybe, you know, but but you need
to at least be putting him on the right path. Okay, and
that's, and obviously there's like, you know, a balancing act about how
much is saying that we're putting him enough on the right path.
But that's, that's the mainstream middle camp. Okay. Then you get the
extreme at the other end that says no, it's not just enough
to say it's to his benefit and we're giving it our okay.
We as the בית דין Beis Din *beis din* have to do
the act of קבלת מצוות *kabbalas mitzvos* for the minor, right? That's
the third approach, the other approach I mentioned. So we are- we
are doing the קבלת מצוות *kabbalas mitzvos* for him. For us to
be able to legitimately say we are being מקבל מצוות *mekabel mitzvos*
for the minor, we have to know for certain, as certain as
you can know, that he's actually going to live a life of
שמירת מצוות *shemiras mitzvos*. So we'll only convert children in completely observant
homes, right? And so that's how you get a fascinating range of
three major different positions within what are the standards for a- for
גירות קטן katan's *geyrus katan*. Okay, yes, דוב *Dov*.
Yeah, I just want to clarify the term הפקר *hefker* here, whether
it has to do with the עבד *eved*- yeah, הפקר *hefker* at
first I thought was like a הפקרות *hefkerus* from doing any מצוות
*mitzvos*, but it's more about sexual acts.
It- yeah, it has more of an emphasis on sexual acts, right.
It's not limited to that.
But, you could have the חיוב *chiyuv* to do מצוות *mitzvos*, the
קבלת מצוות *kabbalas mitzvos* sort of implicit in the concept of הפקרות
*hefkerus*, but that's not the- yeah, yeah.
And it's talking not about- again, about an act of קבלה *kabbalah*,
just a reality of what it means. But you're right, meaning yeah
about sort of right, what the- what the demands are upon you.
Yeah.
It was a מעשה שהיה *Ma'aseh Shehayah*, I was
on such a בית דין Beis Din?
*beis din*. Of- of גירות קטן katan? *geyrus katan*? Yeah, with- and
that was exactly the question. And the person who convened the בית
דין Beit Din? *beis din* asked exactly those questions.
And which one? So the middle group, whether it'll be a likely
for him
to- the middle, right, because this- this person took that middle position.
The family was not- was not שומר שבת *shomer Shabbos*, they were
not committed
to
כשרות
*kashrus*, but they were going to send to a Jewish day school.
Right. And based on, and based on the fact that they were
going to send to a Jewish day school, the head of the
בית דין Beit Din *beis din* accepted the conversion of the child.
Right. That often, yeah, that's- that's like a pretty, right, that's a
pretty mainstream middle position. Although again, you know, people ask what does
that mean? Does it mean the house like on שבת *Shabbos* looks
totally like a weekday? Is there some elements of שבת *Shabbos*? Is
there some- is there some like- you having lobster every night for,
you know what I mean? So obviously the idea is to create
a, not necessarily fully observant home, exactly, but a Jewish. Yeah, to
have a Jewish home and right, that's
a very powerful concept that
you have with the family and it makes like I can imagine
and what that does to their sense of commitment to that therefore.
Yeah, yeah,
two questions.
One is, you know, let's say the kid is kicking and screaming,
this is the last thing I want. We say your דעת da'as
doesn't matter?
Yeah, so that right, so that's a good point. Normally of course
we wouldn't say זכין zachin if the person is present and protesting.
זכין zachin is only if the person is not protesting. But you're
right, I mean, legally what's quite likely is that we would ignore
even the קטן's katan protest because we would just say his current
דעת da'as, has no legal implication, you know, significance. But it's a
good point, it's a good question, right? What if you have the
מחאה mecha'ah of him as a קטן? Katan We're going to see
the מחאה mecha'ah of him as a גדול gadol in a minute.
Let me ask one part of that question. Worst-case scenario is let's
say he has no father, right? So the mother, like you know,
for instance, going back to my model which I know the רמבם
Rambam you said doesn't really hold by that, but you know, like
when you think of the minor girl getting married with no father
around, the mother and the brother do it. So, you know, again,
so even if there's no father, why can't the maternal knowledge still
be sufficient?
Yeah, so that's a good question. Right, רשי Rashi's already is implicitly
מחדש, mechadesh, which is maybe not such a חידוש chiddush that you
don't need בית דין Beit Din, when there's a biological father. Why
don't you say the same thing in the case of a mother?
Even if we said this as both father and mother, in a
patriarchal structure, we defer to the father, but if there's no father,
why shouldn't... it's a good question, but the reality is there's no
case, I mean, that's why רשי's Rashi case is so bizarre. There's
no case of a biological mother that's also legally recognized as her
mother, right? Because for the biological mother would be... I mean, well
that's not true if they're both currently non-Jews, right? They're both currently...
but if they're both currently non-Jews, what happened to the father? Anyway,
so yes, that's a good... right, what if the non... what if
the father is not the Jewish father, but the father is the
biological non-Jewish father? Does that eliminate the need for בית דין? Beit
Din Right, so that's the question you're asking by the mother. It's
a good question, you know? But yeah, I don't know, this is
that's... look, the reality of the patriarchy is that we're less inclined
to sort of recognize the mother's role even in those cases. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara's says like this. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. לימא מסייע ליה. Leima mesayei lei.
Let's come and try to support this. הגיורת והשבויה והשפחה שנשתחררו ושנתגיירו
פחותות מבת שלש שנים ויום אחד. Hagiyores vehashvuyah vehashifcha shenishtachraru veshenisgayeru pachutos
mibas shalosh shanim veyom echad.
So here we have a case of a קטן katan that converted
under three years old. How did that happen? It must be that
בית דין can supervise this. מאי לאו דבלא דעת דעת בית דין?
Mai lav delav da'as da'as Beis Din? Isn't it that you did
it with the intention of בית דין? So the גמרא Gemara says,
לא הכא במאי עסקינן בגר שנתגייר הוא ובניו ובנותיו עמו. Lo hacha
bemai askinan beger shenisgayer hu uvanav uvenosav imo. This is a case
where a convert came with his kids and they're all coming to
convert at the same time. דניחא להו במאי דעביד אבוהון, Denicha lehu
bemai de'avid avuhon,
because in that case they want what their father wants. So if
the father's converting, they want it too. So in that case we
might not have to provide our דעת, we might be able to
say that there it's clear enough, like again, you know, why... that
now normally again, we would ignore what the minor would say, but
here what we're saying is that objectively we can assume that any
kid would want to convert if the father is converting. And therefore
we can say we can recognize it that legally you have the
will of the child or something that represents the will of the
child because anybody would want it. But in a case where you
don't have such circumstances like that, it's not clear that we can
provide the necessary will or approval. Okay, this by the way might
be why רשי said there was no father, not to deal with
a case of a Jewish father coming to convert his kids or
a non-Jewish father converting them when he's not. He might just have
been trying to say we're not dealing with a case the גמרא's
Gemara going to get to later where the father is converting at
the same time of the kid. Okay. Anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. הא ניחא דניחא להו במאי
דעביד אבוהון. Ha nicha denicha lehu bemai de'avid avuhon. אמר רב יוסף,
Amar Rav Yosef, and this is what רב יוסף Rav Yosef said,
הגדילו יכולים למחות. Higdilu yecholim limchos. But
by the way, though I should say that the issue that still
could then be applied to the case of the Jewish father is,
if you say that every minor whose father is converting would want
to convert with his father, then you could say that any minor
whose father is a Jew would want to be Jewish like his
father. Of course what if the mother is not Jewish? Oh who
knows. Okay. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara. says like this. So אמר
רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, said רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, הגדילו יכולים
למחות. Higdilu yecholim limchos.
Since you represented their intent and their will, when they actually become
adults and legally are entitled, you know,
at their will, you know, has legal significance, so then they can
actually object. Okay, and they can basically say, thanks but no thanks.
You know, you did that for me, but I'm telling you now
it was not to my benefit and now my statement matters because
I'm an adult. Okay, so for example, let's say David here wanted
to give me, you know, his brand new Ferrari. Okay, because he's
so much appreciated my דף יומי Daf Yomi שיעור. shiur.
What? Here are the keys.
Here are the keys. So I wasn't around. So Michael was there.
So he said, here Michael, take possession of the keys and of
the deed to my Ferrari for Rabbi Linzer, it's his birthday, it's
a special present. And Michael did it. So we would say that
works. זכין לאדם שלא בפניו. was I didn't appoint him as a
שליח, shaliach, but he represented my side, it's to my benefit, he
can act on my behalf. Okay, then Michael comes and says look
at what David gave you. I said, oh no, שונא מתנות יחיה,
Soneh matanot yichye, you know, I don't accept any gifts. That's completely
against my religious philosophy. I absolutely refuse to accept that from David.
So do I say tough luck, it's still mine? Or we say
no, because he did it on my behalf, when you actually are
able to ask me if I tell you that I don't want
it and it's not to my benefit, then we say so he
never retrospectively, we can't say he was acting on my behalf. That's
the normal logic. We don't say I own it and now I
have to be מפקיר mafkir it. Okay, if I actually took the
keys and said thank you, I can't change my mind. But if
at the first time I was made apprised of the situation, I
said no, that's not to my benefit, then it didn't work. So
the גמרא Gemara says that's what happens when the kid grows up.
You converted him, representing his side, acting on his behalf. Now he's
it's as if he's present because he's an adult. If he could
say I didn't want it, you didn't do it for my benefit,
so then we'll get to that, yes. So then it doesn't work.
Okay, so there's a moment where the kid can actually refuse.
What about if he's adopted by בית דין? You know, doesn't that
sort of override everything? We say like, for instance, הפקר בית דין
הפקר.
Hefker Beit
Din Hefker.
They can take away my property.
Can they make him
a Jew against his will?
Yeah, it's not that.
Sometimes it's בית דין as a concept. Like you know, here it's
like the very concrete people that are present right there are acting
on their behalf. So it's a case by case situation.
And it sounds like a ברירה. breira.
Sort of like that. We were type of that, yes, exactly. So
the גמרא Gemara says, yeah?
What's the difference between that and a Jew who, when he becomes
an adult, says I don't want to be Jewish and leaves the
state?
Because you were born Jewish and there was no nobody was acting
on your behalf, that's just your reality. Here, what made you Jewish
was an act that was done on your behalf. And when you're
able to to have a say, you're saying I didn't, you know,
I didn't want that act done for me.
In in reality
they're both Jews as minors and they're adults.
Yeah, but one only became a Jew because a particular thing was
done on a particular day that was said to be being done
for his sake. And now he's telling us I don't view that
as being done for my benefit. Okay, you don't have that same
transition point for an guy who's born Jewish.
Even if he didn't have a ברית מילה, Brit Milah, he's still
a Jew.
Anybody who's born Jewish, they just naturally are Jewish. There's nothing they
can say they wanted or didn't want.
But let's say they decide as an adult they reject their Judaism.
But they're not, you can't reject your Judaism.
If you were born with two hands, right, it's like you're 13
years old and you say, you know what, I decide I only
have one hand. What
happens
if a Jew converts to another religion or leaves the religion? Look,
here's the difference. My case of the property. Somebody was born and
he inherited a you know, he was born and he inherited a
Ferrari, right? When he gets an adult he can't say, oh, I
never wanted to own that Ferrari. You could you could give it
away, but you still own it right now. You can't stop ever
having owned it. Right? But in the case here, if somebody took
possession of it for his behalf and then he became an adult
and said I didn't want you to do that for me, then
he wouldn't own the Ferrari. The difference is whether there was a
moment of something of an act that was done that created that
transition and it was done for his sake. Yeah,
exactly,
I object, I object. Now how do we exactly identify that moment?
So let's read a little more in the גמרא.
Gemara At this moment in the סוגיא, Sugya, there's no proof for
like where are we in the ש"ס? Shas?
אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, הגדילו יכולים למחות. Hegdilu yecholim limchot.
He's just telling us a new הלכה. Halacha. Okay, since it's based
on זוכין, Zochin, I'm telling you that when they become an adult
they can object. איתיביה אביי, Eitvei Abaye, איתיביה אביי, Eitvei Abaye, so
Abaye
challenged this. הגיורת והשבויה והשפחה שנפדו ושנתגיירו ושנשתחררו פחותות מבנות שלוש שנים
ויום אחד כתובתן מאתיים. Hagiyorat vehashvuya vehashifcha shenifdu veshenitgayeru veshenishtachreru pechutot mibnot
shalosh shanim veyom echad, ktuvatan matayim.
So in this case they converted less than three years, their כתובה's
ktuva 200. וסלקא דעתך הגדילו יכולים למחות, Visalka da'atach hegdilu yecholim limchot,
if they can object and reverse it when they become an adult,
so יהבינן לה כתובה דאזלה ואכלה בגיותא? yahavinan lah ktuva de'azla ve'achla
begiyuta?
So here a man married this convert who converted under the age
of three, presumably through בית דין, okay, and now he divorced her.
You're going to give her the כתובה, ktuva, 200 זוז, zuz, and
now she and that all happened by the time she was ten
years old, she had a very eventful life. And now she became
בת מצווה Bat Mitzvah and now she reversed her Judaism. So how
could we have paid her out her כתובה ktuva ten years old
if it might be that she'll retrospectively turn out to have been
a non-Jew, right? Would we do that? Would we allow a כתובה
ktuva to be paid if it could be that it will turn
out that she was a non-Jew? All right, well okay, that's an
interesting question too. All right, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, לכי
גדלה. Lechi gadla. No, what we mean is we'll pay her the
כתובה ktuva when she becomes an adult. So if he married her
and divorced her under ten years old, he won't pay out the
כתובה ktuva yet until she becomes a בת מצווה Bat Mitzvah and
she doesn't object. And then we say, ah, now your Jewish status
is sealed. There's no way to reverse it now because you became
a בת מצווה Bat Mitzvah and you didn't object. Now we'll pay
out the כתובה. ktuva. Okay, לכי גדלה. Lechi gadla. So the גמרא
Gemara says, לכי גדלה נמי ממחה ואפקא? Lechi gadla nami mimcha ve'afka?
So why can't she object even after she becomes an adult? She
can object and walk out. גמרא Gemara says no, כיון שגדלה Kivan
she'gadla שעתא אחת ולא מיחתה, shaata achas velo michasa,
since she grew up, she became an adult for that initial moment,
and she did not object. So in that case, שוב אינה יכולה
למחות Shuv eina yechola limchos from that point on, she can't object
anymore. Once she was apprised of the situation and again going back
to my Ferrari case, Michael said, I took possession of that Ferrari
for you, here is a key, and I say thank you very
much, I can't say a week later, oh no I never wanted.
Okay, my opportunity to have said that it was not on my
behalf was when I was apprised to that situation. If I did
not object then, then it's sealed and we cannot reverse it. So
therefore the scenario is that she became an adult, she didn't object
to being Jewish, and at that stage we pay out the כתובה.
kesuvah. Now, by the way, first of all, Rabbi Shmuel Herzfeld emailed
me as I was walking to שול shul, this morning, says, I
don't understand, how did she get married as a minor? Right, if
it says that we're talking about once she was married as an
adult, fine, she's an adult Jewish woman when she's married. But how
can if she's here she's a minor, she doesn't have a father,
she doesn't have a mother who's Jewish, who married her?
Oh, that's a pretty good question, I don't have the answer to
that. Anyway, okay, that's just one footnote question have to figure that
one out. But anyway, the interesting question for us in terms of
גר קטן Ger Katan is, what is this שעתא אחת? shaata achas?
What is this original moment that you have an opportunity
to object? So if you take a look at the side here
and in the right-hand margin, we have a line from the
תוספות ישנים, Tosafos Yeshanim, קשה אם כן מתי תדע שעת המחאה דתנא
אינה יכולה למחות ויש לומר כגון שהתחילה מן הגיות יום לפני גדלותה
וכן נהגה יום יומיים אחר גדלותה. Kasha im kein masai teida shaas
hamacha'ah d'tana eina yechola limchos v'yeish lomar kegon she'hitchila min hagi'yut yom
lifnei gadlusa v'chein nohaga yom yomayim achar gadlusa. So one answer is
that right before her בת מצוה Bat Mitzvah she started acting like
a non-Jew. And then she continued acting like a non-Jew a day
after her בת מצוה. Bat Mitzvah. So that constitutes the מחאה. macha'ah.
Others say, no, you have to actually apprise them of the situation
and give them an opportunity. So often in the case of a
גר קטן, Ger Katan, there's a whole question is the rabbi supposed
to take the גר Ger this child who's converted as a קטן
katan into his office before his or her בר או בת מצוה
Bar or Bat Mitzvah and say, oh, just checking, do you want
to remain Jewish? And then the kid says,
yes, and then having that they said yes right after, then it's
considered like that they're apprised of the
situation, then they became בר בת מצוה, Bar Bat Mitzvah, they didn't
do anything to counter that. Of course, what happens if the parents
adopted the kid as an infant and they have yet to tell
the kid that he's adopted, how do you have that conversation? Of
course, nowadays that's much less frequent that parents don't tell the kids
that they're adopted than it used to be. But that becomes a
whole issue, and also what does it mean? Or some say you
don't have to have the conversation, the person just has to continue
living a Jewish life in the time right after the בר בת
מצוה. Bar Bat Mitzvah. What's continue living a Jewish life? Let's say
the kid was brought up in a home that wasn't observant, so
they very much identify as Jewish, but let's say they go after
the בר בת מצוה Bar Bat Mitzvah and they go get a
cheeseburger. Is that a מחאה? macha'ah? It's a מחאה macha'ah if you're
in a פרום frum house and you go and get a cheeseburger,
that would constitute a מחאה. macha'ah. But if that's not the but
if that's not the but if that's not the context of your
Judaism, it might not constitute a מחאה. macha'ah. So that raises a
lot of these interesting questions of how do we translate this in
our scenario.
So מחאה macha'ah didn't mean that you have to go to the
בית דין and say I don't want this.
Is that what you're saying? Right.
Yeah, you think it would be.
Yeah,
that's true too. You mean in addition to the question of what's
the key moment, you could also say is there a formal scenario
of doing the מחאה? macha'ah? Like to whom do you do this
מחאה? macha'ah? Right. All of these things are vague.
Or it could just be your
action between you and yourself, like I sneak away middle of the
night, eat my cheeseburger.
I assume you need at least there to be some type of
עדות edus to it, but you might not need a formal מעשה
מחאה. maaseh macha'ah. But it's a good question. I mean, that's the
question that nobody really can figure out and there's a lot of
answers to it. Okay, so מתיב רבא, Masiv Rava, so now רבא
Rava asks a similar question. אלו נערות שיש להם קנס, Eilu naaros
she'yeish lahen knas, the פרק perek we're going to get to later,
the following young women have a
קנס knas if they are raped, then there's the קנס knas of
fifty כסף kesef that we mentioned before. And also there it has
to be a נערה naarah who's a virgin. Okay, so the following
women have a
קנס. knas. הבא על הממזרת ועל הנתינה, Ha'ba al hamamzeres v'al hanesina,
so even if she's a ממזרת mamzeres or נתינה, nesina, which is
also a woman a person she's not allowed to marry, so even
though in case of rape the מצוה mitzvah is that he has
to marry her, and there are times he can't marry her because
she's like a ממזרת, mamzeres, nevertheless the payment of the קנס knas
still applies. ועל השפחה V'al hashifcha and then ועל הכותית, v'al ha'kusis,
we won't worry about that for now. ועל הגיורות ועל השבויה ועל
השפחה שנפדו ושנתגיירו ושנשתחררו פחות מבנות שלוש שנים ויום אחד. V'al hagiyoros
v'al hashvuya v'al hashifcha she'nifdu v'she'nitgayru v'she'nishtachreru pahos mibnos shalosh shanim v'yom
echad. The three in our משנה Mishna whose their status changed under
three years old, so they're still considered virgins, so there there is
the קנס. knas. So רבא, Rava, here's רבא's Rava question. He says,
ואי אמרת הגדילו יכולים למחות, V'ei amart higdilu yecholim limchos, if they
can object and reverse their conversion when they become adult, יהבינן לה
קנס? yehavinan la knas? How would we give this woman who or
young girl who converted under three years old, now she's let's say
twelve, how would we give her a קנס knas if she can
always object? Okay, and then we'll have it retroactively it'll turn out
that we paid her a קנס knas to a woman who was
a non-Jew.
יהבינן לה קנס דאזלה ואכלה בגיות. Yehavinan la knas d'azla v'achla b'giyut.
it'll turn out that she'd be able to benefit from as a
non-Jew? Retrospectively she'll she'll object and become a non-Jew. גמרא Gemara says
לכשתגדל. Likhshe-t'gdal. Alright, we'll wait to pay the קנס knas until she
becomes an adult. לכשתגדל, Likhshe-t'gdal, would you wait until she becomes an
adult? נמי ממחי ונפקא, Nami mamchei v'nafka, she can also object and
leave. No, כיוון שגדלה שעה אחת ולא מיחתה, Kivan she-gadla sha'ah achas
v'lo michtah, once there was one moment and she didn't, שוב אינה
יכולה למחות, Shuv einah yecholah limchos, she can't do it anymore. אביי
Abaye לא אמר כרבא, lo amar k'Rava, why was אביי Abaye not
bothered by the case of the קנס? knas? Why was he only
bothered by the case of the כתובה? kesuvah? התם קנס היינו טעמא,
Hasam knas hainu ta'ama, because by קנס knas it didn't bother him
if it might wind up going to her as a non-Jew. שלא
יהא חוטא נשכר, She-lo ye-hotee niskar, this guy raped a woman or
young girl, right? So even if it winds up that the money
winds up retroactively will go to her that she'll have become a
non-Jew, you know what? More important is that he paid the money.
It's less important who got the money.
You shouldn't reward a sinner.
Right, by not having to pay. רבא Rava לא אמר כאביי, lo
amar k'Abaye, why wasn't רבא Rava bothered by אביי Abaye about paying
out the כתובה kesuvah of two hundred? Why did he only ask
about the case of קנס? knas? Because רבא, Rava, כתובה היינו טעמא
שלא תהא קלה בעיניו להוציאה. Kesuvah hainu ta'ama she-lo te-he kallah be-einav
l'hotzi-ah. Same issue. I really don't care so much about whether retroactively
she'll be not Jewish. I am more concerned that the husband, that
wives in general should be protected. So that's a little bit different.
That's not just I need him to pay. That's like here's this
woman, right? On the one hand I could say she shouldn't get
a כתובה kesuvah because maybe money will go to her and she
won't be deserving or whatever and she'll turn out she was not
Jewish. Or I could say more important to me than that possibility,
נבך nebach she'll get some money that's not coming to her, is
the fact that she deserves to be protected in her situation as
a wife who could maybe easily be divorced and I have to
ensure that that to me is what's more significant. Maybe sometimes נבך
nebach money will be paid that shouldn't have been paid, but more
significant is to be sure that women are protected in their marriage.
One more thing about this issue about גר קטן, ger katan, תוספות
Tosafos says also related to the מיחוי. micha. Look at תוספות לכשתגדל
Tosafos likhshe-t'gdal by the case of the קנס. knas. ואם
תאמר והלא כבר גדולה היא שהיא נערה, V'im tomar v'lo kvar gedola
hi she-hi ne-arah, כיוון שהיא בת קנס, kivan she-hi bas knas, right?
So if you pay the קנס knas of fifty כסף, kesef, it's
only by a נערה. ne-arah. נערה ne-arah is twelve years old. So
why does the גמרא Gemara say she still has a chance to
be ממחה? moche? What do you mean she has a chance to
be ממחה? moche? The whole case of קנס knas is that she's
twelve years old and a day. So he says, ומפרש ר"י לכשתגדל
ונהגה מנהג יהודית. U'mifa-resh Ri likhshe-t'gdal v'naga minhag yehudis. Okay, that it's
not enough and this connects to the other thing. It's not enough
to just not be ממחה, moche, to just have your בת מצווה,
Bat Mitzvah, you have to do something that shows like the opposite
of a מיחוי. micha. So that's the question: do you need the
affirmation or do you need an objective מיחוי? micha? So he says,
basically here's this girl on the day of her בת מצווה Bat
Mitzvah before she even made it to שול, shul so that would
have been her affirmation of her Judaism or whatever, she got raped.
Okay, but if she had just had one day or one minute
after her בת מצווה Bat Mitzvah where she had actually done something
Jewish, then it would have been, then she couldn't have been ממחה.
moche. Okay, so that gets to the whole question of how do
you define what constitutes מיחוי micha or when מיחוי micha is no
longer meaningful.
Yes? Question, like sometimes you're sort of like on autopilot, you're not
necessarily meaning to affirm it.
Yeah, but it doesn't matter.
It's to me because like your parents, so you do, you know
what I mean? Like you go to שול and then you go
home and watch TV
and eat your cheeseburger. So is that really an affirmation of a
Jewish lifestyle?
So that's why sometimes like I said sometimes the rabbi sort of
sees it as his responsibility to inform the person. That if you're
informed about that and you go ahead and continue doing it. But
yeah, that gets to the question. But גמרא Gemara. never says you
need a positive affirmation, it just says that you need them not
to be
ממחה. moche. I understand, but only to achieve a standard of אי-מיחוי,
i-michui, not to necessarily achieve a standard of positive affirmation. That's the
way you get to אי-מיחוי. i-michui. So yes, that's the whole question
what the standard is. Yes, Dov.
I don't understand Shmuel's question exactly. The שפחה shifcha is a שפחה
כנענית? shifcha knaanis? Yeah.
Okay, so we're not asking from the שפחה. shifcha. She becomes Jewish
by being free. We're asking about the non-Jewish child who's under three
years old.
The גיורת? giyores? Yeah. So his question is only on the גיורת
giyores of those three? Yeah. Okay, I just wanted to remember.
All right, so that was talk about כתובות דף י"א קטן. Kesuvos
daf yud alef katan. That little סוגיא sugya here is
so huge implications for realities nowadays in terms of a גרות. gerus.
Okay. משנה. Mishnah. הגדול שבא על הקטנה. Ha-gadol she-ba al haktana. Now
we get to the question of what does it mean to be
a virgin?
Okay, is it a physiological state of not having a hymen broken?
Is it a question about not having had sex? Okay, so let's
take a look. הגדול
שבא על הקטנה, Ha-gadol she-ba al haktana, so if an adult had
sex with a minor, right, which is obviously something unconscionable, but that's
the case גמרא Gemara. is dealing with. וקטן שבא על הגדולה, V'katan
she-ba al hagedola, or a minor had sex with an adult woman.
So both of those cases it is not, and we mean by
a minor girl under three and by a minor boy we mean
under nine. So both of those cases it is not legally considered
an act of sex. It might not be an act of sex
but if it's an adult man with a minor... but if it's
a minor boy with an adult woman, it would still rupture the
hymen. I mean even an adult man with a minor girl would
rupture the hymen but
the גמרא Gemara. again... Right, in these cases you have it that
two things. Number one is let,
don't confuse me right now. Number one is that because one of
them is a minor, which is considered under the age of what
הלכה Halacha recognizes as an act of sex, either the boy's under
nine or the girl's under three, it's not an act of sex.
The only question you're left with is but did it rupture the
hymen, okay? But let's but the first point in the משנה Mishnah
is it's not an act of sex. And then it says ומוכת
עץ, umukas eitz, a woman who literally is, you know, injured with
a piece of wood, which basically means that the hymen was ruptured
not through an act of sex. All those three cases כתובתן מאתיים,
kesuvosan masayim, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. They get a full
כתובה kesuvah of two hundred. So for רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, right,
basically it is the effect is not defined by the presence of
excuse me a second,
virginity is not defined by the presence of the hymen. Virginity is
defined by not having had an act of sex. Okay, and in
all those three cases it was not halachically an act of sex,
even though in some of them the hymen might have broken. Okay,
so that's a pretty consistent position of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. וחכמים
אומרים, vachachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim say, מוכת עץ כתובתה מנה. mukas
eitz kesuvosah maneh. So they say no, actually, it's having the hymen
intact is part of the definition. So if a woman had the
hymen ruptured because of this case of מוכת עץ, mukas eitz, she
only gets a hundred. So yes, not a virgin is not only
not having had sex, a virgin is also having had the hymen
intact. Okay, the question obviously is going to be, so why isn't
the case about קטן הבא על הגדולה katan haba al hagedolah also
not like a מוכת עץ, mukas eitz, right? That should have ruptured
the hymen too. Okay. בתולה אלמנה גרושה וחלוצה מן הנישואין, besulah almonah
grushah vechalutzah min hanisuin, now if a woman was a בתולה, besulah,
but she had been not only had קידושין, kiddushin, she had נישואין,
nisuin, right? They had חופה, chuppah, they went to the ייחוד yichud
room, they went to the guy's house, and then he had a
heart attack before they actually had sex. Okay, so yes she or
whatever, divorced her before they had sex. So she's a בתולה besulah
from or and she's a בתולה besulah
and a אלמנה גרושה וחלוצה, almonah grushah vechalutzah, widow, divorcee or חלוצה
chalutzah after the חופה, chuppah, after נישואין, nisuin, where it's assumed they're
having sex even though in this case they didn't, כתובתן מנה. kesuvosan
maneh. There they only get a hundred, because there even though in
practice she's still a בתולה, besulah, both in terms of sex and
in terms of the hymen or whatever, because she was in a
legal state where basically it was assumed that she's living a sexual
life, so therefore that defines her as a בעולה. beulah. We'll discuss
that more later,
but that's formalistic.
It's yeah, okay, but או כללא, o klala, לא פלוג, lo plug,
we're not going to go try figure out every woman after the
חופה, chuppah, did you actually have sex or not? You know, we
sort of just have to assume as a blanket rule that you
did. Okay, we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara ואין להם
טענת בתולים, ve'ein lahem ta'anas besulim, so since there they're assumed to
have sex, the husband can't complain to have not to have had
sex during their first marriage, the husband can't complain if they turn
out, you know, to have not been a virgin. He could say,
"Well, I knew you were married to the guy, but he had
a heart attack right there under the חופה, chuppah, so I thought
that you were still a בתולה." besulah. No, it comes as a
package. If you're only going to pay if the כתובה kesuvah is
only going to be a hundred because legally we're assuming that they've
had sex, then you can't complain if it turns out she wasn't
a virgin.
The whole נדה niddah might be different, right?
All right, all right, yeah, all right, we'll take a look. It's
okay, we'll see when we get through the גמרא. Gemara הגיורת והשבויה
והשפחה שנפדו ושנתגיירו ושנשתחררו יתר משלוש שנים ויום אחד, hagiyores vehashvuyah vehashifchah
shenifdu veshenisgayru veshenishtachraru yeser mishalosh shanim veyom echad, if these women were
were taken captive or converted or freed after three years and a
day, so then it's assumed in their state as being not Jewish
or slave or captive they've had sex, and over three years it's
considered an act of sex and it's considered that the hymen won't
grow back. In that case כתובתן מנה ואין להם טענת בתולים. kesuvosan
maneh ve'ein lahem ta'anas besulim. The כתובה kesuvah is only a hundred,
and again, because the כתובה kesuvah is a hundred, the husband can't
complain if it turns out they're not a virgin. You can't have
it both ways. If you're only paying a כתובה kesuvah of a
hundred because we're assuming not a virgin, then you can't say, "Yes,
but I was assuming nevertheless she was a virgin." No, it comes
as a package. Okay, גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar
Rav Yehudah amar Rav, קטן הבא על הגדולה עשאה מוכת עץ. katan
haba al hagedolah asoah mukas eitz. So if you have this case
in our משנה mishnah that a minor had sex with an adult
woman, so even if it's not a halachic act of sex because
he's under nine, but still she's considered a מוכת עץ, mukas eitz,
she's considered no longer a virgin because he ruptured the hymen, presumably
it ruptured the hymen. So the גמרא Gemara says כי אמריתה קמיה
דשמואל, ki amrisah kamei deShmuel, but when I said this in front
of שמואל Shmuel says רב יהודה Rav Yehuda because this is what
he said in the name of רב, Rav, אמר אין מוכת עץ
בבשר. amar ein mukas eitz bebasar. No, through a through flesh, through
an actual act of sex, you can't make somebody a מוכת עץ.
mukas eitz. Now what does this mean? What does this mean? I
mean if it actually ruptured the hymen, why should her status be
less of a מוכת עץ mukas eitz because it came through an
act of sex? I mean the whole point of מוכת עץ mukas
eitz is to sort of make her you know possibly not considered
a virgin. Why should there be this weird middle state? Well, legally
it wasn't an act of sex, but because the hymen ruptured not
through some type of of of of of an external object... but
through actual act of intercourse even though הלכתית halachicly we don't call
it ביאה, biah, then you're neither a מוכת עץ muksas etz nor
somebody who's had an act of sex and you're a virgin. Really?
That's just completely bizarre. I understand that if the hymen ruptures through
some other means she wouldn't be a virgin, it ruptured this way
she is a virgin? So Tosafos doesn't accept that even though Rabbi
Dov does and if you look at Tosafos, Tosafos says: ושמואל אמר
אין מוכת עץ בבשר. v'Shmuel amar ein muksas etz babasar. בלא הפשיר
בתולין איירי. b'lo hipsheer besulin ayrei. We have to say it's a
scenario where the hymen didn't rupture. דאי בהפשיר, D'ee b'hipsheer, if the
hymen ruptured, למה יש לה להיות פחותה ממוכת עץ? lama yesh la
lihyos p'chusa mi'muksas etz? He can't understand Tosafos, so he can't understand
Shmuel, so Rabbi Dov thinks we can be completely formalistic about it.
There's something, right, who normally doesn't like formalism, here he's happy with
it. Okay. If you're having intercourse, then you have to define it
as sex and the act and sex makes her not a virgin
and this isn't sex because he was a minor. And if it's
some type of act, some type of external object and some type
of injury or accident, then that can make her a virgin because
it because it ruptured the hymen. If it happened to be that
the hymen ruptured through an act of intercourse that we don't recognize
as ביאה, biah, then she's still a virgin. Right.
A lot of pages issue with it, it's something nice for the
woman.
Okay, anyway, I got to tell you, I, I, I,
to me, I go like Tosafos. Totally agree. I go like Tosafos,
okay. If there's, anyway, so that's the debate of Rav and Shmuel
in this middle case. Is she considered, does she have a status
of a מוכת עץ? muksas etz? I'm going to go with Tosafos
that the, that the hymen is still intact. So the hymen is
still intact, but he's a adult, but it's a, it's a minor
boy with an adult woman, does it put her into the category
of מוכת עץ? muksas etz? Okay, so let's take a look.
So you're saying it's Rabbi Winsor and Tosafos against Rabbi Dov?
Exactly. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Wait, there's one thing I just don't understanding. So if it was,
let's say, a nine-year-old boy and a girl less than twelve?
Could we not do with your case, let's focus on the case
in גמרא. Gemara איכא דמתני להא שמעתא באפי נפשה. Ika d'matni l'ha
shma'ata b'apei nafsha. Some taught this without Rav Yehuda reporting what he
spoke to Rav and Shmuel about but independently באפי נפשה. b'apei nafsha.
קטן הבא
על הגדולה. Katan haba al hagedola. So you have the case a
minor under nine years old boy has sex with an adult woman
which הלכתית halachicly is not considered ביאה. biah. Okay, it's not considered
an act of sex. So רב אמר עשאה מוכת עץ, Rav amar
asaa muksas etz, even if it's not considered ביאה, biah, she still
is in the category of מוכת עץ. muksas etz. Okay, of a
woman who's considered to be, it's not ביאה, biah, but she's considered
to have lost like not have, not be a virgin, not through
an act of sex, but not to be a virgin through a
something else, which is מוכת עץ. muksas etz. Okay, that's what it's
considered. ושמואל אמר אין מוכת עץ בבשר. v'Shmuel amar ein muksas etz
babasar. No, if it's not an act of sex, it's nothing. מתיב
רב אושעיא. Metiv Rav Oshaya. So Rav Oshaya asked on Rav as
we're going to see. קאמר משנה: Ka'amar mishna: גדול הבא על הקטנה
וקטן הבא על הגדולה, Gadol haba al haktana v'katan haba al hagedola,
an adult man with a minor girl or a minor boy with
an adult
woman, ומוכת עץ, u'muksas etz, כתובתן מאתיים, ktubatan matayim, all these you
get two hundred, דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, because Rabbi Meir
says if you don't have an act of sex she's still considered
a virgin. Okay, וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, and the חכמים Chachamim say,
מוכת עץ כתובתה מנה. muksas etz ktubata maneh. By the case of
מוכת עץ, muksas etz, she gets a hundred. Now here's the question:
why did the חכמים Chachamim only argue by מוכת עץ? muksas etz?
They should, why didn't they also argue
by קטן הבא על הגדולה? katan haba al hagedola? According to Rav
that says that makes her like a מוכת עץ, muksas etz, right,
so they should have had the case of a קטן הבא על
הגדולה. katan haba al hagedola. That's the question. Michael? Okay, stop it
with your they're both under eight. We'll get to we can talk
about that later. Okay, אמר רבא, amar Rava, so says Rava, הכי
קאמר: hachi ka'amar: גדול הבא על הקטנה ולא כלום.
gadol haba al haktana
v'lo klum.
דפחות מכאן כנותן אצבע בעין דמי. d'pachot mikan k'noten etzba ba'ayin dami.
So Rava says you're right. We're going to reread the משנה. Mishnah.
The משנה Mishnah sounds like קטן katan and a גדולה gedola is
not a מוכת עץ muksas etz because the חכמים Chachamim don't disagree
with it, but we're going to reread the משנה Mishnah and we're
going to divide, and as Mike maybe this is what you meant
Michael, so I'm sorry. There are three cases. We'll start first with
the גדול gadol and the קטנה. ktana. Okay, so the גדול gadol
and the קטנה, ktana, that everybody agrees is nothing. It doesn't, it's
not הלכתית halachicly an act of sex and it doesn't even do
anything to the hymen because ולא כלום. v'lo klum. Why is it
ולא כלום? v'lo klum?
דפחות מכאן כנותן אצבע בעין דמי. d'pachot mikan k'noten etzba ba'ayin dami.
That when the girl's under three, it's like putting a finger in
the eye. You know, you put your finger in the eye, it
doesn't rupture the eye, it's just the eye bounces back, it's not
a sharp object, it's just your finger, okay. Maybe causes you to
tear or something, but everything in the end gets back better. Okay,
so basically the hymen therefore restores and it's not an act of
sex and it doesn't do anything to the hymen, so everybody agrees
with a גדול gadol and a קטנה, ktana, it has no, it's
nothing. I mean it's a despicable act, but it's nothing in regard
to this. Okay, so that's כנותן אצבע. k'noten etzba. וקטן הבא על
הגדולה, v'katan haba al hagedola, and how about a קטן with a
גדולה? gedola? It's not an act of sex, but it could have
the potential of rupturing the hymen. So in that case, עשאה מוכת
עץ. asaa muksas etz. So that will be treated as a
מוכת עץ. muksas etz. ומוכת עץ גופה פלוגתא דרבי מאיר ורבנן. u'muksas
etz gufa plugta d'Rabbi Meir v'Rabbanan. Oh and by the way, this
is the debate: Rabbi Meir says מוכת עץ muksas etz is two
hundred and the רבנן Rabbanan say a hundred. So the basic point
is is that the משנה Mishnah seems to say that מוכת עץ
muksas etz is the case that's debated, which implicitly says that the
קטן and the גדולה, gedola, the minor... minor boy and the adult
woman is not a מוכת עץ. mukat etz. But רבא's Rava answer
is, no, it's they're really being bundled together. Okay, when they're debating
מוכת עץ, mukat etz, they're really debating both of those cases. Of
course, the משנה mishna reads much better according to שמואל. Shmuel. Okay,
let's take a look. So that is what we have: the debate,
is that put her in the category of מוכת עץ? mukat etz?
So according to the רבנן Rabbanan that say that a מוכת עץ
mukat etz is considered to be not a בתולה, besulah, she would
not be a בתולה. besulah. It's not considered to be a, what
do you call it, an act of sex, but is it enough
to be considered like having the same effect of מוכת עץ mukat
etz to make her not a בתולה besulah according to the חכמים?
Chachamim? And that's what they're debating. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר
רמי בר חמא מחלוקת כשהכיר בה.
Amar Rami
bar Chama machlokes k'she'hikker bah.
The debate here... fine. So now we can put aside that whole
case which is disturbing and whatever. And let's just talk about the
issue of מוכת עץ. mukat etz. There's a debate of רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir and the חכמים Chachamim whether מוכת עץ mukat etz gets
200 or 100. Here's the question, very important question: does the man
know what the story is, right? So is it that when he
married her, did he realize that she no longer had her hymen
intact? Simple case, she's never had sex, so she's a virgin from
that perspective, but she doesn't have the hymen intact. She's a מוכת
עץ. mukat etz. If she tells this to the guy, does she
get her 200 according to the חכמים? Chachamim? Is the חכמים Chachamim
saying only a hundred because it was something other than he expected?
Or even the חכמים Chachamim say even if he knows, he only...
she only gets a hundred? She's not a virgin from a physiological
perspective, she gets only a hundred. So that's the question. Let's take
a look. Is it only with an element of מקח טעות? mekach
taus? אמר רמי בר חמא מחלוקת כשהכיר בה. Amar Rami bar Chama
machlokes k'she'hikker bah. The debate of if she only gets a hundred
as a מוכת עץ—again, mukat etz never had sex, but a מוכת
עץ—that mukat etz debate is כשהכיר בה, k'she'hikker bah, is that he
knew it. And even though he knew it, רבנן Rabbanan are still
saying she only gets a hundred. רבי מאיר מדמי לה לבוגרת ורבנן
מדמי לה לבעולה. Rebbi Meir medamme lah l'bogeres v'Rabbanan medamme lah l'beulah.
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says it's like a בוגרת, bogeres, so yes,
even though she doesn't have a hymen she's no different than a
girl who became more mature, whose hymen has thinned out and
she's still considered to be a בתולה. besulah. Or is she like
a woman who's had sex? How do you put a woman who
has never had sex, but there's been some violent sort of event
that ruptured the hymen? Do you put her in the non-בתולה besulah
category or in the more natural בתולה besulah category? There are two
women that don't have the hymen intact, not to the same degree.
One who experienced some type of a traumatic event, some type of
a violent event, and not through an act of sex, and the
other who just became an adult and the hymen thinned out. Where
do you put the case
of—I'm sorry,
I said that wrong.
Let's read the גמרא Gemara again. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like
this: מחלוקת כשהכיר בה דרבי מאיר מדמי לה לבוגרת ורבנן מדמי לה
לבעולה. machlokes k'she'hikker bah d'Rebbi Meir medamme lah l'bogeres v'Rabbanan medamme lah
l'beulah. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says she's like a בוגרת, bogeres, so
yes, even though she doesn't have a hymen, she's no different than
a girl who became more mature, whose hymen is thinned out and
she's still considered to be a בתולה. besulah. And the רבנן Rabbanan
say no, the hymen was ruptured through some type of external object,
even if it wasn't an act of sex, and therefore she only
gets a hundred, she's not a virgin. אבל לא הכיר בה דברי
הכל ולא כלום. Aval lo hikker bah divrei hakol velo klum. But
if he didn't realize, the husband, that this had happened to her,
then he could say: oh, it was all false premises, and she
gets nothing. Okay, so there's
a difference between being not necessarily deceived, but misinformed, and being a
טעות, taus, and being an error, and it's not what I expected.
And then he can say the whole thing was a mistake and
therefore zero, because I was expecting not just that you hadn't had
sex, I was expecting that the hymen was intact.
That's, okay, maybe they agree to that. They disagree when he knows
the facts and which category this puts her into.
And now the גמרא Gemorah just spells out what that debate would
be, which logical category to put her into. So we'll just read
that. Okay, so גמרא Gemorah says like this: רבי מאיר אמאי מדמי
לה לבוגרת מדמי לה לבעולה? Rebbi Meir amai medamme lah l'bogeres medamme
lah l'beulah? Why does רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir treat her like a
בוגרת? bogeres? I mean, why not treat her like a בעולה? beulah?
The hymen's been ruptured. So no, בעולה עביד בה מעשה בידי
אדם, beulah isavid bah maaseh bidei adam, because a woman who's had
sex, it's not just the hymen's been ruptured, there's been a human
act of intercourse. הא לא עביד בה מעשה בידי אדם. ha lo
isavid bah maaseh bidei adam. Here, yes, there was something extraneous that
went into her body and ruptured the hymen, but nevertheless it wasn't
sex. So that's an easy one. If it wasn't sex, she's still
a virgin in my book. That's what רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says.
Okay, therefore 200. ורבנן מדמי לה לבעולה מדמי לה לבוגרת? V'Rabbanan medamme
lei l'beulah medamme lei l'bogeres?
Why not put her in the בוגרת bogeres category? It is true
she didn't have sex. So we have another woman who didn't have
sex who's still considered a בתולה, besulah, a woman who's more physically
mature that maybe the hymen is thinned out, but she's still considered
to be a בתולה. besulah. גמרא Gemorah says no: בוגרת לא עביד
בה מעשה כלל הא עביד
בה
מעשה. bogeres lo isavid bah maaseh klal ha isavid bah maaseh. No,
there nothing actually happened, you know, that sort of simulated the act
of sex as it were.
That has
been ruptured, that would be in our case category a בעולה. beulah.
So basically what the גמרא says is, it's a formal question of
how do you define non-virgin? Do you define it as a woman
who's had sex, which is what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, or
do you define it a woman who's had some act that has
ruptured the hymen, even not through sex? That's what the rabbis say,
and they debate when the man knows the story. But if he
doesn't know the story, then they could say, oh, the whole thing's
a big mistake, and then she would get nothing. And now the
גמרא tomorrow, or the remainder of today, but anyway, as the גמרא
continues, we'll look at it from the other possibility, that maybe the
whole debate is the opposite, when he didn't know what the story
was, and therefore the question was, to what degree can he say,
I never would have wanted this? But maybe if he knew what
the story was, maybe she would get full according to everyone.
Everyone would agree.
Right. So there's two ways of looking at it, whether it's about
him saying, this wasn't what I expected, and that's the issue, or
whether it is what he expected, but what formal category do we
put her into? The virgin category or the non-virgin category?
The virgin knowledge or lack knowledge.